Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection
1967-2013
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
3.5 linear feet (8 boxes)
This is a collection of documents relating to various long range strategic planning efforts at Xavier University. The collection encompasses those periods from the 1960s through 2010.
XUA-57
History of Xavier University Long Range Planning Efforts
Long range planning efforts at Xavier University were concerted efforts to focus upon the goals, needs and resulting resources needed to enhance overall institutional wellness and growth at Xavier University. As such these efforts at times preceded capital gifts campaigns. Areas of attention included academics, marketing, and other areas.
Scope and Content
This collection reflects strategic planning activities during the tenures of various Xavier presidents, beginning with that of Paul O'Connor, S.J. in the 1960s and ending with current president Michael Graham, S.J. in 2010.
Statement of Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically by the tenure of individual Xavier presidents. Those periods are: Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., Presidency, 1955-1972 (collection begins with 1967); Robert W. Mulligan,S.J., Presidency, 1972-1981; Charles F. Currie, Presidency, 1983-1986; Albert J. DiUlio, S.J., Presidency, 1986-1990; James H. Hoff, S.J., Presidency, 1991-2000; Michael J. Graham, S.J., Presidency, 2000-present.
Restrictions on Access
This collection has restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio) -- Planning
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1955-1972, O'Connor Presidency) Milford Workshops, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This folder contains the Milford documents for the years 1967 through 1969.
  During the presidencies of Fathers O'Connor and Mulligan, a workshop or conference took place almost every year in late summer at the Men of Milford Retreat House. Since these workshops were long range strategic sessions, the materials pertaining to them have been placed here.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1955-1972, O'Connor Presidency) Milford Workshops, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains the Milford documents for the years 1970 and 1971.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Milford Workshops, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder contains materials for 1972 and 1976-1977. Intervening years are presently missing.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Planning and Development Committee (1968-1973), 2013 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This folder contains notes written by university archivist Thomas Kennealy,, S.J. concerning the Planning and Development Committee. This committee was heavily involved in long range strategic planning from 1968 to 1973.
  For documentation from the Xavier University Planning and Development Committee, see archival collection XUA-18, Planning and Development records.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1976-1981) Projections, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  During the presidency of Robert Mulligan, S.J., Xavier embarked on a long range strategic planning project called The Five Year Plan which led up to the Sesquicentennial Campaign, a capital gifts campaign. The university enlisted the aid of the consulting firm Northlich,Stolley, Inc. for this project.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1972-1981) Northlich, Stolley Reports, 1976 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  This folder contains the report "Strength & Weakness Analysis for Xavier University."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1976-1981) Northlich Stolley Reports, 1976 May 26; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  This folder contains the following reports: 1. Xavier Communications Plan; 2. A Proposal for Development of a Marketing & Communications Program for Xavier University.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1976-1981) Northlich Stolley Reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This folder contains a document entitled "1977 Xavier Marketing Plan."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1976-1981) Northlich Stolley Reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  This folder contains copy two of the report entitled "1977 Xavier Marketing Plan."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1972-1981, Mulligan Presidency) Five Year Plan (1976-1981) Academic Plans 1978-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  This folder contains academic plans for the three colleges of the university, 1978 to 1983. It is not clear what part these plans played in the Five Year Plan.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1982-1985,Currie Presidency) Mission Statement and SWOTS Analysis, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  This folder contains the following documents: 1. Correspondence of Charles Currie, S.J. regarding the strategic planning process (includes apparent attachments); 2. Correspondence of Charles Currie, S.J. regarding goals and objectives for 1984-1985. Includes attachment "Xavier University Goals and Objectives, 1984-85;" 3. Document "Xavier University Goals and Objectives, 1985-86;" 4. Document "Recommendations of the Xavier University Space Committee, May 1984;" 5. Document "SWOTS Analysis."
  During the presidency of Charles Currie, S.J. (1982-1985) several steps were taken in preparation for a long range strategic planning project which was not completed. This box contains records and documents concerning these preliminary steps.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1982-1985, Currie Presidency) Departmental and Divisional Goals, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  This folder includes completed surveys of Xavier departments and divisions as to their goals. Limited correspondence is also included.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1982-1985, Currie Presidency) Planning Committees, 1985 February-May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  This folder includes: 1. Minutes of the Planning Committee; 2. Document "University Planning Committee Report Abstract" (April 19, 1985); 3, Document: "A Report to the University Planning Committee, Xavier University, Long Range Goals" (May 1, 1985); 4. Correspondence.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1986-1990, DiUlio Presidency) Xavier Board of Trustees, Marketing and Admissions Subcommittee, 1986 March-May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  This folder contains correspondence stemming from the activity of the Xavier Board of Trustees Marketing and Admissions Subcommittee.
  During the presidency of Albert DiUlio (1986-1990), a considerable amount of long range strategic planning in various forms took place in preparation for the capital gift campaign called The Cornerstone Campaign (1986-1992). This box contains the records and documents pertaining to the strategic planning done during these years.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1986-1990, DiUlio Presidency) Xavier Board of Trustees Marketing and Admissions Subcommittee, 1986 May-July (Box 4, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. Correspondence stemming from the activities of the Xavier University Board of Trustees Marketing and Admissions Subcommittee; 2. Document "Xavier University: What is the Product; What is the Brand" (Tatham-Laird & Kudner, June 20, 1986).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1986-1990, DiUlio Presidency) College of Arts and Sciences Department and Program Review (Box 4, Folder 3)
  This folder contains survey information completed by the various departments and programs of the Xavier University College of Arts and Sciences. The information had been solicited by the Office of the Academic Vice President.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1986-1990, DiUlio Presidency) College of Business Administration and College of Social Sciences Department and Programs (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1986-1990, DiUlio Presidency) Program Review Committee (Box 4, Folder 5)
  This folder contains correspondence and reports associated with the Program Review Committee.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Xavier University Strategic/Long Range Planning Retreat (January 25-26, 1992); 2. University Planning and evaluation Process: 1993-94 Plan (1992); 3. University Planning Process and Priorities FY 1993-94 (1992).
  During the presidency of James Hoff, S.J. (1991 to 2000) a long range strategic planning project called XU 2000 was undertaken in preparation for the capital gifts campaign called The Century Campaign (1996-2001). Phase One of the project ended with acceptance by the Board of Trustees on July 15, 1991 of the report of the University Futures Committee. The report was entitled "Xavier University: a Proposal for the Future." Phase Two followed immediately thereafter and included all the materials in this box and the next.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. "Xavier University: Environmental Assessment, Update 1992, Higher Education"; 2. "Guidelines for Strategic Planning, Process and Priorities, FY 1994-2000."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  This folder contains the following documents: 1. "University Relations and Advancement, Strategic Plan, 1994-2000;' 2. "Xavier University Division of Academic Affairs, 1993-94 Plan;" 3. "Xavier University Department of Intercollegiate Athletics, Strategic Plan FY 1994-2000;" 4. "Strategic Planning Process: Critical Success Factor, Student Development."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1993; undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  This folder contains: 1. "Financial Administration: Divisional Strategic Plan and Priorities for 1994-2000;" 2. Memorandum from the Office of the President (July 6, 1993) re University Strategic Plan; 3. "Draft, Xavier University Strategic Plan FY 1994-2000."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1994; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  This folder contains: 1. News Release concerning the Board of Trustees approving the strategic plan; 2. "Xavier University Strategic Plan FY 1994-2000."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1994 April 6 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  This folder contains the "Xavier University Image Study" by Thomas J. Hayes (April 6, 1994).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1994 April 6 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  This folder contains the continuation of the "Xavier University Image Study" by Thomas J. Hayes (April 6, 1994).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1994 April 6; undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1." Xavier University Image Study" by Thomas J. Hayes (continuation); 2. "Do's and Don'ts in Marketing Research" by Thomas J. Hayes (1994?; 3. Surveys.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (1991-2000, Hoff Presidency) XU 2000 Plan, 1994; 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  This folder contains the following: 1. Brochures; 2. Charts (May 2, 1994); 3. "Xavier University Division of Academic Affairs, 2000 Plan;" 4. "Status: Strategic Plan for Academic Excellence" (Office of Academic Affairs (December 1, 2000); 5. "Academic Affairs Strategic Plan, 1994-2001."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) History of Strategic Planning, 2001 to 2010, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  This folder contains the following documents: 1. "Xavier University's Strategic Plan in Historical Perspective" (draft of 9/17/2007 and final of 9/27/2007)' 2., "Xavier University's Strategic Plan in Historical Perspective" (6/29/2010).
  During the first nine years of the presidency of Fr. Michael Graham (2001-2010), a considerable amount of long range strategic planning took place in various forms. This was in preparation for the capital gifts campaign called To See Great Wonders (2006-2011). This box and the following box contain documents pertaining to this strategic planing effort.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Academic Vision Committee, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  This folder contains various communications and documents. Also includes document "Xavier University's Academic Vision."
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency), 2003 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. Limited communications; 2. "All Committee Reports" (June, 2003).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis, 2002 August (Box 7, Folder 4)
  This folder contains Richard Pulskamp's "Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis" (August, 2002) (Section 1)
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis, 2002 August (Box 7, Folder 5)
  This folder contains the continuation of Richard Pulskamp's "Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis" (August, 2002) (section 2)
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis, 2002 August (Box 7, Folder 6)
  This folder contains the continuation of Richard Pulskamp's "Xavier University Steering Committee: Internal and External Situational Analysis" (August 2002) (Section 3)
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Scannell and Kurz Report, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  This folder contains the 2006 Scannell and Kurz report (includes draft report).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Academic Advising Report (Part 1), 2006 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  This folder contains the report prepared by the office of Academic Advising for the visit by the consulting firm Scannell and Kurz in 2006 (part 1).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Scannell and Kurz Reports (Part 2), 2006 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  This folder contains the report prepared by the office of Academic Advising for the visit by the consulting firm Scannell and Kurz in 2006 (part 2).
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Scannell and Kurz Reports, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  This folder contains the report prepared by the Learning Assistance Center for the visit by the consulting firm Scannell and Kurz in 2006.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Scannell and Kurz Report, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  This folder contains the report prepared by the office of Student Success and Retention for the visit by the consulting firm Scannell and Kurz in 2006.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Scannell and Kurz Reports, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  This folder contains the report prepared by the English as a Second Language Program (ESL) for the visit by the consulting firm Scannell and Kurz in 2006.
- Long Range Strategic Planning (2001-2010, Graham Presidency) Environmental Scan and Other Documents, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  This folder contains 1. A document entitled "Environmental Scan and Market Niche Analysis 2009 (Office of Decision Support, November 18, 2009); 2. Brochure "Changing Lives in the Jesuit Tradition;" 3. Photocopy of Powerpoint slides of program entitled "Xavier University's Strategic Plan."